<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>My Notes</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/</link><description>Recent content on My Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/drawing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/drawing/</guid><description>Graphics # 1 5 0 4 2 6 3 7 + z + y + x v 1 v P 0 X v 3 E y v e 2 R e f r a c t i o n R e f l e c t i o n Complex # &amp;amp; A M S i o i q f b B x u j o e a ( - x d r a &amp;gt; e f R &amp;gt; c o C n u o b ( n r ) ) d n e e J d r o s i n N o R D t o i u a a n g d d l o i t n e D i a g o n a l s C V u e r r v t e i d c a l n o t A N C : o u l d r r i A a / I v n s i n e e h s t d - e - t r l B i h i i s i o n ' s r e q n .</description></item><item><title>Crews (2018)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/crews2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/crews2018/</guid><description>Development of a Collisionless Plasma Kinetic Solver and an Investigation of One-Dimensional Plasma Waves and Instabilities # Shielded potential of a test electron:
\[\phi(r) = \frac{-e}{4 \pi \epsilon_0 r} e ^{- r / \lambda_D}\] where the Debye length is \( \lambda_D = \sqrt{\frac{\epsilon_0 T_e}{ n_e e}} \) . The mean free path between large-angle collisions is estimated as
\[\lambda_{mfp} \sim \frac{\epsilon_0 T_e ^2}{\phi_e n_e \log ( \Lambda)}\] where \(\phi_e = e^2 / 4 \pi \epsilon_0\) are the constants from the Coulomb force law.</description></item><item><title>Datta (2021)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/datta2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/datta2021/</guid><description>\[\] A Domain-Hybridized Plasma Model Using Discontinuous Galerkin Finite Elements # Models # Keep in mind that the behavior of a plasma is primarily determined by the ratio between a spatial length of interest and the following reference lengths. The appropriate model for describing a plasma depends on the regime defined by these lengths.
Reference length Degree of magnetization Larmor radius \( r_L \) Charge separation Debye length \( \lambda_D \) Collisionality Mean free path \( \lambda_{mfp} \) Continuum Kinetic Model # The continuum kinetic model is the most complete description, taking into account the forces acting upon each particle:</description></item><item><title>Goedbloed (2019)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/goedbloed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/scratch/goedbloed/</guid><description>\[\] Thermonuclear fusion and plasma confinement # Nuclear reactions release net energy if there is a mass defect, i.e. if
\[(m_A) &amp;#43; m_B) c ^2 &amp;gt; (m_C &amp;#43; m_D) c^2\] In laboratory fusion, hydrogen isotopes are considered, where the deuterium-tritium reaction is the most promising one for future reactors:
\[D^2 &amp;#43; T^3 \rightarrow He ^4 (3.5 MeV) &amp;#43; n (14.1 MeV)\] This yields two kinds of products, viz. \( \alpha \) particles which are charged so that they can be captured by a confining magnetic field, and neutrons which are electrically neutral so that they can escape from the magnetic configuration.</description></item></channel></rss>