<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Introduction on My Notes</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/</link><description>Recent content in Introduction on My Notes</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://peppyhare.github.io/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to Computational CFD</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-1/</guid><description>20.1 Introduction to Computational CFD # What is computational fluid dynamics? Put simply, it&amp;rsquo;s the use of computers to obtain a numerical solution to the governing equations of fluid dynamics. As always, the numerical solution is an approximation to the real solution to the equations, but additionally those equations are themselves only an approximation of the real physics.
We will be interested in speeds much less than \( c \) (\( 3 \cdot 10^8 m/s) \) and distances much greater than the atomic radius \( \alpha_{bohr} = 5 \cdot 10^{-11} m \).</description></item><item><title>Mathematical review</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA556/ch01-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA556/ch01-1/</guid><description>\[\] Mathematical review # We&amp;rsquo;re starting off with some mathematical foundation to ensure we&amp;rsquo;re all on the same page before we start talking about waves and collisions.
Fourier Series / Spectral Analysis # First, let&amp;rsquo;s not get confused between Fourier series and Fourier transforms. A Fourier series is the breakdown of a function defined on a finite interval into &amp;ldquo;frequency components.&amp;rdquo; For example, if we have \( f(x) : x \in [a, b] \), a Fourier series for \( f(x) \) pulls apart the discrete frequency components of the \( e^{ikx} \) modes that make up the function.</description></item><item><title>Rules of thumb</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-0/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-0/</guid><description>Rules of thumb # \[\] Jarboe&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Rules of Thumb&amp;rsquo; - basic associations and concepts to keep in mind when working with fusion plasmas
Rule 1 In event counting measurements the uncertainty in event rate is equal to the square root of the number of events detected. A trade off is made between signal resolution and time resolution Rule 2 The total E and M force on a volume of plasma can be computed from surface values through \( \vec F = \int \overline{T} \cdot \vec n \dd V \) Rule 3 Magnetic field has a tension and isotropic pressure</description></item><item><title>Syllabus</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/01-syllabus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/01-syllabus/</guid><description>\[\] Syllabus # Learn the basis of common computational methods used for plasma physics, specifically, methods applied to magnetic confinement, plasma thrusters, and astrophysics. Learn the regions of applicability of the various computational methods. Implement a computational method to simulate plasma kinetics using an electrostatic PIC approach. Simulate plasma dynamics using a PIC code and an MHD code. Motivation # As a motivation for studying computational methods for plasmas, consider the task of analytical methods for arriving at closed-form expressions of the plasma properties.</description></item><item><title>Syllabus</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/01-syllabus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/01-syllabus/</guid><description>Syllabus # The course topics planned for this section are (in rough order):
Particle Model, Boltzmann-Maxwell Model, Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) Model, Region of Validity, Common Assumptions, Ideal MHD Model, General Properties (Equilibrium, Boundary Conditions, Conservation Laws, &amp;ldquo;Frozen-In&amp;rdquo; Flux)
Ideal MHD Equilibrium, Virial Theorem, Magnetic Flux Surfaces
One-Dimensional Equilibria, Theta-Pinch, Z-Pinch, Screw-Pinch, Safety Factor q
Two-Dimensional Equilibria, Toroidal Geometry, Grad-Shafranov Equation, Closed Flux Surfaces, Safety Factor q, Magnetic Shear, Magnetic Well, Shafranov Shift, Spheromak, Reversed Field Pinch (RFP), Tokamaks, Stellarators (Elmo Bumpy Torus)</description></item><item><title>Syllabus</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/01-syllabus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/01-syllabus/</guid><description>\[\] Syllabus # The goals of this course are:
To teach the function of diagnostic components, and the specific plasma mechanisms that are being measured. You will be come familiar with the analysis procedures required to get (often indirect) measurements. To appreciate uncertainty and error quantification in reporting experimental measurements. This course will use I.H. Hutchinson, Principles of Plasma Diagnostics as the primary text, with the standard R.J. Goldston and P.</description></item><item><title>Vector Algebra</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-1/</guid><description>1.1 Vector Algebra # 1.1.1 Vector Operations # If you walk 4 miles due north and then 3 miles due east (Fig. 1.1), you will have gone a total of 7 miles, but you&amp;rsquo;re not 7 miles from where you set out-you&amp;rsquo;re only 5. We need an arithmetic to describe quantities like this, which evidently do not add in the ordinary way. The reason they don&amp;rsquo;t, of course, is that displacements (straight line segments going from one point to another) have direction as well as magnitude (length), and it is essential to take both into account when you combine them.</description></item><item><title>Differential Calculus</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-2/</guid><description>1.2: Differential Calculus # 1.2.1: &amp;ldquo;Ordinary&amp;rdquo; Derivatives # Suppose we have a function of one variable, \( f(x) \). Question: what does the derivative \( \dv{f}{x} \) do for us? Answer: It tells us how rapidly the function \( f(x) \) varies when we change the argument x by a tiny amount, \( \dd{x} \)
\[\dd{f} = \left( \dv{f}{x} \right) \dd{x} \tagl{1.33}\] In words: If we increment x by an infinitesimal amount \( \dd{x} \), then \( f \) changes by an amount \( \dd{f} \); the derivative is the proportionality factor.</description></item><item><title>General Diagnostic Considerations</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/02-diagnostic-considerations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/02-diagnostic-considerations/</guid><description>General Diagnostic Considerations # \[\] First, let us categorize some broad categories of items to consider when we think about plasma diagnostics by asking a few questions:
Which plasma properties do we want to measure?
Densities for individual species, velocity, temperature (moment measurements). In the case where a plasma is not thermal (Maxwellian), we may need to measure species distribution function \( f_s (\vec v) \) Plasma content, i.e. species concentrations, \( Z_{eff} \) (which is a determining factor in resistivity and radiation power) Plasma currents, current densities, electromagnetic fields.</description></item><item><title>Governing Equations</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-2/</guid><description>Governing Equations # Continuity
\[\pdv{\rho}{t} &amp;#43; v \cdot \grad \rho = - \rho \grad \cdot v\] Momentum:
\[\rho \left( \pdv{v}{t} &amp;#43; v \cdot \grad v\right) &amp;#43; \grad p - \frac{1}{\mu_0} (\curl \vec B) \cross \vec B = \div \vec T \] \[\vec T = \text{ viscous stress tensor }\] \[\frac{1}{\mu_0} \curl \vec B = \vec j = \text{ current density }\] Magnetic Field
\[\pdv{B}{t} - \curl ( v \cross B) = - \curl \left[ \frac{\eta}{\mu_0} (\curl \vec B) \right]\] \[\eta = \text{ electrical resistivity }\] Energy:</description></item><item><title>Plasma Models</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/02-plasma-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/02-plasma-models/</guid><description>Plasma Models # \[\] First, let&amp;rsquo;s get a working definition of &amp;ldquo;plasma&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;a quasi-neutral gas of charged and neutral particles that exhibit collective behavior.&amp;rdquo; Many of the approaches we will describe will also apply to non-neutral plasmas. Plasmas are composed of particles (electrons, ions, neutrals) which interact through electric and magnetic fields and through collisions. Therefore, the plasma can be modeled as individual particles.
Plasmas exhibit collective behavior due to the long-range forces from EM field interactions.</description></item><item><title>Plasma Models</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/02-plasma-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/02-plasma-models/</guid><description>Plasma Models # Working towards MHD # Let&amp;rsquo;s start from a full-particle description with the goal of reaching a continuum description (kinetic model). Then, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at the forces on the separate species and form a multi-fluid model, finally simplifying to a single-fluid MHD model.
The most important question to ask ourselves is &amp;ldquo;when is this model going to be useful?&amp;rdquo; The MHD model is the mathematical model for magnetized plasmas that are treated as a fluid.</description></item><item><title>Statistical Mechanics</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-1/</guid><description>10-1 Statistical Mechanics # 10.1.1 Very Large Numbers # Before getting started with real plasma physics concepts, we need to quickly review some statistical mechanics with the goal of deriving the Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution.
As we all know, if we have \( N \) unique objects, there are \( N! \) ways of arranging them. If \( n_1 \ldots n_k \) are identical with N things, the number of combinations is</description></item><item><title>Integral Calculus</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-3/</guid><description>1.3: Integral Calculus # 1.3.1: Line, Surface, and Volume Integrals # In electrodynamics, we encounter several different kinds of integrals, among which the most important are line (or path) integrals, surface integrals, and volume integrals.
Line Integrals # A line integral is an expression of the form
\[\int_a ^b \vec{v} \cdot \dd{\vec{l}} \tagl{1.48}\] where v is a vector function, \( \dd \vec{l} \) is the infinitesimal displacement vector and the integral is to be carried out along a prescribed path P from point a to point b.</description></item><item><title>Magnetic Field Diagnostics</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/03-magnetic-field-diagnostics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/03-magnetic-field-diagnostics/</guid><description>B-dot Probe Diagnostics # Faraday&amp;rsquo;s law is the basis for magnetic field coils:
\[\int \pdv{\vec B}{t} \cdot \dd \vec S = - \oint \vec E \cdot \dd \vec l = - V_{emf}\] For a rigid, perfectly conducting loop of N turns in the presence of a changing magnetic field,
\[V_i = \oint \vec E \cdot \dd \vec l = - \pdv{\Phi}{t} = - \pdv{}{t} \int \vec B \cdot \dd \vec s = - N A \frac{\int \pdv{\vec B}{t} \cdot \dd \vec s}{\int \dd \vec s} \\ \rightarrow V_i \propto \dot{B_{avg}}\] where \( B_{avg} \) is the area-averaged magnetic field aligned to loop.</description></item><item><title>Particle in Cell Model</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/03-pic-method/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/03-pic-method/</guid><description>\[\] Particle-In-Cell Model (Particle model revisited) # The order of magnitude issues with the N-body model prevent a direct application in even simple laboratory plasmas. In a plasma with \( N = O(10^{21}) \), we have interactions on the order of \( O(10^{42}) \) making direct computation completely impractical.
We can instead use representative particles with the same charge to mass ratio, but fewer (\( N = 10^3 \sim 10^7 \)) particles.</description></item><item><title>Plasma Fluid Model</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/03-plasma-fluid-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/03-plasma-fluid-model/</guid><description>Plasma Fluid Model # We take velocity moments of each of the pieces of the kinetic model:
distribution function, \( f_\alpha \) \( \rightarrow \) fluid variables Boltzmann Equation \( \rightarrow \) governing equations describing the evolution of the fluid variables. Starting with the zeroth moment (integral) of the distribution function:
\[\int f_\alpha (\vec x, \vec v, t) \dd \vec v = n_\alpha(\vec x, t)\] 1st Moment (momentum):
\[m_\alpha \int \vec v \cdot f_\alpha(\vec x, \vec v, t) \dd \vec v = \vec p_\alpha (\vec x, t) = m_\alpha n_\alpha \vec v_\alpha\] which is to say that the velocity is the 1st moment divided by the zeroth moment</description></item><item><title>Reduced Models</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-3/</guid><description>20.3 Reduced Models # Further simplifications to the fluid models provide equations that are easier to solve. But we have to make sure that the reduced models (anything that&amp;rsquo;s not the full equation system) still capture the relevant physics of the problem.
Let&amp;rsquo;s assume the (2D) flow is
irrotational \( (\curl v = 0) \) isentropic steady-state This lets us apply potential flow theory. Since the flow is irrotational, the curl of the velocity field is zero, so we can define a potential</description></item><item><title>Review of E&amp;M</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-2/</guid><description>10.2 Review of E&amp;amp;M # Homework group: just me n leek42@uw.edu
Realistically, all of the E&amp;amp;M review comes from https://peppyhare.github.io/griffiths-em/
10.1.1 Maxwell Stress Tensor # The Maxwell stress tensor encompasses the way that electromagnetic fields an exert forces/stresses in 3D space:
\[\vec p = \text{ momentum }\] The basic force laws of E&amp;amp;M are
\[\dv{\vec p}{t} = q \left( \vec E &amp;#43; \vec v \cross \vec B \right)\] On an element of volume, the change in momentum is</description></item><item><title>Curvilinear Coordinates</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-4/</guid><description>1.4: Curvilinear Coordinates # 1.4.1: Spherical Coordinates # You can label a point P by its Cartesian coordinates (x, y, z), but sometimes it is more convenient to use spherical coordinates \( (r, \theta, \phi) \); \( r \) is the distance from the origin (the magnitude of the position vector r), \( \theta \) (the angle down from the z axis) is called the polar angle, and \( \phi \) (the angle around from the x axis) is the azimuthal angle.</description></item><item><title>Electrostatic Diagnostics</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/04-electrostatic-diagnostics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/04-electrostatic-diagnostics/</guid><description>\[\] Langmuir Probes # Langmuir probes are the oldest and simplest plasma diagnostic: You simply insert an electrode into the plasma and measure the \( I \)-\( V \) curve. Doing so is fairly simple, but the probe measurements are often difficult to interpret, since extracting accurate plasma properties from measurements can be challenging.
Consider a probe inserted into a steady-state plasma. We assume that there is an electrode (e.</description></item><item><title>Equation Types</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-4/</guid><description>Equation Types # PDE&amp;rsquo;s can be classified as elliptic, parabolic, or hyperbolic. The type of equation will suggest the choice of an appropriate algorithm.
The equation type can change for different flow parameters, or even for different regions within the same domain.
20.4.1 Scalar Equations # All of the scalar equations in fluid dynamics can be written in canonical form as the following 2nd order PDE.
\[a \phi_{xx} &amp;#43; b \phi_{xy} &amp;#43; c \phi_{yy} &amp;#43; d \phi_x &amp;#43; e \phi_y &amp;#43; f \phi = g\] where \( x, y \) are any two independent variables.</description></item><item><title>Lagrange Multipliers</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch10-3/</guid><description>Lagrange Multipliers # When we have a problem of variation where one function is maximized or minimized subject to a constraint imposed by another function
\[f(x_1, \ldots x_n) \rightarrow \text{ function }\] \[g(x_1, \ldots, x_n) = 0 \rightarrow \text { constraint }\] Without the constraint we would have the problem
\[\delta f = \pdv{f}{x_1} \delta x_1 &amp;#43; \ldots \pdv{f}{x_n} \delta x_n\] \[\pdv{f}{x_i} = 0 \qquad i = 1 \ldots n\] and apply any of our multivariate optimization strategies to solve.</description></item><item><title>PIC - Example Implementation</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/04-pic-example/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/04-pic-example/</guid><description>\[\] Notes and details for an electrostatic PIC implementation.
Dimensions and Normalizations # To make the relevant physics as easy to model and visualize as possible, let&amp;rsquo;s choose units such that time is normalized by the plasma frequency and length scales of interest are of order unity. This will make things a lot easier to plot and interpret in the long run, even though normalizations like \( m = q /(q / m) \) seem arcane.</description></item><item><title>Two-Fluid Plasma Model</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/04-two-fluid-plasma-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/04-two-fluid-plasma-model/</guid><description>Two-Fluid Plasma Model (ions-electrons) # Restricting our multi-species fluid model to ions and electrons, what can we say about wave behavior in a magnetized 2-fluid plasma? Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a cold plasma approximation ( \( p = 0 \) ) and neglect collisions. The momentum equation reduces to
\[m_\alpha \left( \pdv{\vec v_\alpha}{t} &amp;#43; \vec v_\alpha \cdot \grad \vec v_\alpha \right) - q_\alpha (\vec E &amp;#43; \vec v_\alpha \cross \vec B) = 0\] From here on out we can avoid some clutter (and wrist strain) by dropping the \( \alpha \) subscripts and acknowledging that we have sets of equations for ions and electrons.</description></item><item><title>Index of Refraction Measurements</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/05-index-of-refraction-measurements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/05-index-of-refraction-measurements/</guid><description>\[\] Index of Refraction Measurements # The refractive index is defined as the speed of light (in vacuum) over the phase velocity \( n = \frac{c}{v_{\phi}} \), \( v_\phi = \omega / k \). Recall that in vacuum the phase velocity is just the speed of light (\( n = 1 \) in vacuum). In a plasma, we know that the dispersion relation will be substantially different.
In most materials, \( n &amp;gt; 1 \), but from our crude diagram we can expect plasmas to have \( n &amp;lt; 1 \).</description></item><item><title>Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) Model</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/05-mhd-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/05-mhd-model/</guid><description>Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) Model # Applying approximations to the two-fluid plasma model will allow us to arrive at a single-fluid (center-of-mass) description. The result is the ideal magnetohydrodynamic model (MHD).
First, define the MHD variables:
\[\text{mass density:} \qquad \rho = n_i m_i &amp;#43; n_i m_e\] \[\text{fluid velocity:} \qquad \vec v = \frac{n_i m_i \vec v_i &amp;#43; n_e m_e \vec v_e}{n_i m_i &amp;#43; n_e m_e}\] \[\text{current density:} \qquad \vec j = q_i n_i \vec v_i - e n_e \vec v_e \rightarrow \vec v_e = \frac{q_i n_i \vec v_i}{e n_e} - \vec j / e n_e\] \[\text{total pressure:} \qquad p = p_i &amp;#43; p_e = n_e T_e &amp;#43; n_i T_i\] \[\text{total temperature:} \qquad T = \frac{n_i T_i &amp;#43; n_e T_e}{(n_i &amp;#43; n_e)/2}\] Now let&amp;rsquo;s begin applying asymptotic approximations.</description></item><item><title>Multidimensional Electrodynamic PIC</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/05-electrodynamic-pic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/05-electrodynamic-pic/</guid><description>\[\] Multidimensional Electrodynamic PIC # Now that we&amp;rsquo;ve touched on each of the components of a 1-dimensional electrodynamic PIC method, let&amp;rsquo;s try to move our model into a full multidimensional one. The main difficulty in moving from 1D to 2D/3D is the increased variety of waves present in the solution.
Field Equations # The EM fields must be solved for the full Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations, not just Poisson&amp;rsquo;s equation, in order to capture the full dynamics.</description></item><item><title>Panel Method</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch20-5/</guid><description>20.5 Panel Method # Panel methods are a classical approach to solving flow problems that is still very useful today when finding solutions to even very complicated geometries. You represent a body as a series of panels.
A few definitions first: we say a source panel of strength \( \lambda \) (units m/s) is defined by:
\[\phi_p = \frac{1}{2 \pi} \int \lambda \ln (r) \dd s\] \[= \frac{1}{2 \pi} \int \lambda \ln \left( \sqrt{ (x_p - x)^2 &amp;#43; (y_p - y)^2}\right) \dd s\] \[\lambda = 2 u_\lambda\] Approximate a body as a polygon of N sides.</description></item><item><title>The Dirac Delta Function</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-5/</guid><description>1.5: The Dirac Delta Function # 1.5.1: The Divergence of \( \vu{r} / r^2 \) # Consider the vector function
\[\vec{v} = \frac{1}{r^2} \vu{r} \tagl{1.83}\] At every location, v is directed radially outward (Fig. 1.44); if ever there was a function that ought to have a large positive divergence, this is it. And yet, when you actually calculate the divergence (using Eq. 1.71), you get precisely zero:
\[\div \vec{v} = \frac{1}{r^2} \pdv{}{r} \left( r^2 \frac{1}{r^2} \right) = \frac{1}{r^2} \pdv{}{r} (1) = 0 \tagl{1.</description></item><item><title>Wall-supported Plasma</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-1/</guid><description>Wall-supported Plasma # Consider a &amp;ldquo;hot&amp;rdquo; plasma surrounded by a &amp;ldquo;cold&amp;rdquo; wall. What are the properties of the plasma (both electrons and ions) at the wall? The speed of a particle headed towards the wall is
\[\frac{1}{2} m v_{th} ^2 \approx \frac{1}{2} kT \rightarrow v_{th} \approx \sqrt{ \frac{kT}{m}}\] Since electrons are much lighter than ions (\( m_e = m_i / 1800 \) for hydrogen), they are moving much faster and will leave the plasma at a much higher rate than the ions.</description></item><item><title>Boundary Conditions</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/06-boundary-conditions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/06-boundary-conditions/</guid><description>Boundary Conditions # Mathematically, a well-posed problem requires both governing equations and a complete set of boundary conditions (the Cauchy data for the problem). The most common boundary conditions we use are perfectly conducting walls (flux surfaces) or a vacuum region.
Perfectly Conducting Wall # For the case where the plasma extends out to a perfectly conducting (impermeable) wall. Perfectly conducting walls do not support tangential electric field:
\[\left. \vec E_t \right|_{wall} = 0 \quad \rightarrow \quad \left.</description></item><item><title>Collisions</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-2/</guid><description>Collisions # If \( \Lambda \) is large, then small-angle scattering dominates.
\[\nu = \frac{n}{2 \pi \epsilon_0 ^2} \frac{ e^4}{m^2 v_0 ^3} \ln \Alpha \propto \frac{n}{T^{3/2} m^{1/2}}\] Paschen curve for breakdown # Say we have two large parallel plates
You can stay on the g=1 curve by putting a large resistor on your power supply, so it&amp;rsquo;s always running like it&amp;rsquo;s about to break down. Neutral-dominated plasma (neutral resistance).</description></item><item><title>Finite Difference Algorithms</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-1/</guid><description>21.1 Finite Difference Algorithms # Definitions # By definition, Finite Differencing is a method to approximate partial differential equations which we cannot solve, into a system of algebraic equations which we can.
Notation to simplify our representations:
Superscripts: We use superscripts to denote steps in the time domain \( t^n = n \Delta t \). Here \( n = [0, N] \) is the step index and \( \Delta t \) is the time-step \( T/N \) Subscripts: \( x_j = j \Delta x \).</description></item><item><title>Fluid Models for Plasmas</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/06-fluid-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/06-fluid-models/</guid><description>\[\] Motivation for Fluid Models # Up to this point, we&amp;rsquo;ve been discussing particle models, and in particular, kinetic descriptions in which we&amp;rsquo;ve sampled the distribution function at particular locations to get our particles. We retained detailed information about the distribution function by tracking the positions and velocities of these representative super-particles, which should continue to &amp;ldquo;represent&amp;rdquo; the sampled distribution function at all points in time. Tracking this detailed information is computationally expensive, so PIC is limited to small spatial scale or short time scale phenomena.</description></item><item><title>Spectroscopic Measurements</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/06-spectroscopic-measurements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/06-spectroscopic-measurements/</guid><description>\[\] Spectroscopic Measurements # Plasma Self-Emission # Plasmas emit light (electromagnetic radiation) over a broad range of wavelengths. This can be from the X-ray to UV to visible to IR. The emission depends on the plasma constituents, magnetic field, and plasma properties \( n_e, T_e, T_i, \vec v_i \). We should be able to analyze the self-emission to provide a measurements of these properties. These measurements are both rich in information, and completely non-perturbing.</description></item><item><title>The Theory of Vector Fields</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-6/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch1-6/</guid><description>1.6: The Theory of Vector Fields # 1.6.1: The Helmholtz Theorem # Ever since Faraday, the laws of electricity and magnetism have been expressed in terms of electric and magnetic fields, E and B. Like many physical laws, these are most compactly expressed as differential equations. Since E and B are vectors, the differential equations naturally involve vector derivatives: divergence and curl. Indeed, Maxwell reduced the entire theory to four equations, specifying respectively the divergence and the curl of E and B.</description></item><item><title>Equilibrium for Fusion</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/07-equilibrium-for-fusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/07-equilibrium-for-fusion/</guid><description>Equilibrium for Fusion ( \( \beta \) ) # For a fusion device we would like to determine a magnetic configuration that confines plasma while it fuses. At fusion temperatures, the power required to maintain the equilibrium will be substantial. For a device to be useful, the power required to sustain the equilibrium must be less than the power released from fusion. Important loss terms for a confined plasma are transport (thermal conduction primarily) and radiation terms.</description></item><item><title>Explicit Finite Difference Algorithms</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-2/</guid><description>Explicit Finite Difference Algorithms # Explicit Algorithms # Forward Euler (FTFS) # n+1 --------|--------*--------|-------- n --------|--------*--------*-------- j-1 j j+1 \[u_j ^{n&amp;#43;1} = u_j ^n - \frac{a \Delta t}{\Delta x} (u_{j&amp;#43;1} ^n - u_j ^n)\] The accuracy is \( O(\Delta t, \Delta x) \). Previously we saw that the von Neumann stability analysis shows
\[a &amp;gt; 0 \rightarrow \text{ Unconditionally unstable}\] \[a &amp;lt; 0 \rightarrow \left| \frac{ a \Delta t}{\Delta x} \leq 1 \right| \quad \text{ for stability }\] Forward-Time Centered Space (FTCS) # \[u_j ^{n&amp;#43;1} = u_j ^n - \frac{a \Delta t}{\Delta x} \frac{u_{j&amp;#43;1} ^n - u_{j-1} ^n}{2}\] We also found that this is unconditionally unstable.</description></item><item><title>Finite Difference Methods for MHD</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/07-finite-difference-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/07-finite-difference-models/</guid><description>Finite Differencing # So for 1D MHD, we want to derive algorithms to advance the governing equations in time that have the form
\[\pdv{\vec Q}{t} &amp;#43; \pdv{\vec F}{x} = 0\] We can use the advection equation as a model equation: \[\pdv{u}{t} &amp;#43; a \pdv{u}{x} = 0\] which has the general solution \[u(x - at) = \text{const.} = u(x, t=0)\] If we apply a forward Euler finite difference operators to our PDE,</description></item><item><title>Oscillations</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA557/ch11-3/</guid><description>Oscillations # Collision Frequencies # Gases have three degrees of freedom to oscillate, but plasmas have four: the electron fluid adds an additional parameter.
One way to see how the electron fluid oscillates, take a region of plasma and displace the electrons by a distance \( x \) and release. Then, watch how the electrons oscillate.
Gauss&amp;rsquo;s law gives the resulting electric field (same as a parallel-plate capacitor.
\[E = \frac{n e x}{\epsilon_0}\] The restoring force is therefore</description></item><item><title>1-D Equilibria</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/08-1d-equilibria/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/08-1d-equilibria/</guid><description>1-Dimensional Equilibria # The \( \theta \) -pinch # In a \( \theta \) pinch, we have an applied axial field generated by a driven azimuthal current distribution. The way these usually work is that you begin with a plasma generated by some pre-ionization process and zero field. Then you crank up the current to drive an azimuthal current in the plasma (in the opposite direction as the external current).</description></item><item><title>Finite Difference and Finite Volume Methods</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-3/</guid><description>Finite Difference and Finite Volume Methods # Finite volume methods can easily handle arbitrary geometries. You can use arbitrarily shaped cells, irregular meshes, and even unstructured meshes. With an irregular mesh, the cell shapes can distort. In an unstructured mesh, the cell shape can even change. Why would you ever want that, you may ask? Consider a circular shape in the middle of our domain. We&amp;rsquo;ll have a pretty hard time fitting a regular or even irregular mesh to a circle.</description></item><item><title>MHD Equilibria</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/08-mhd-equilibrium/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/08-mhd-equilibrium/</guid><description>Equilibrium Calculations # From physical expectations, elliptic equations result from equilibrium calculations and eigenvalue systems. In general, we can write elliptic equations as \[\vec A \vec x = \vec b\] where \( \vec A \) may be a nonlinear function of \( \vec x \). For example, if we think of Poisson&amp;rsquo;s equation in 1D, \[\dv{^2 \phi}{x^2} = - \rho_c\] and apply finite differencing, \[\frac{\phi_{j&amp;#43;1} - 2 \phi_j &amp;#43; \phi_{j-1}}{\Delta x^2} = - \rho_j\] we get a matrix system \[\vec A \vec x = \frac{1}{\Delta x^2} \begin{bmatrix} -2 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; \ldots \\ 1 &amp;amp; -2 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; \ldots \\ \ldots &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; \ldots &amp;amp; \ldots \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} \phi_1 \\ \phi_2 \\ \ldots \end{bmatrix} = \vec b = - \begin{bmatrix} \rho_1 \\ \rho_2 \\ \ldots \end{bmatrix}\] where \( \vec A \) is a J by J matrix.</description></item><item><title>2D Equilibria</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/09-2d-equilibria/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/09-2d-equilibria/</guid><description>2D Equilibria # Let&amp;rsquo;s connect the ends of our 1D equilibria. Doing so is what gives us inherently toroidal configurations. From the 1-dimensional picture:
\[\vec j \cross \vec B = j_\theta B_z - j_z B_\theta \\ = \grad p = \dv{p}{r}\] we move to an axisymmetric 2-dimensional torus, replacing our cylindrical coordinate system with a toroidal one
\[\vec j \cross \vec B = \vec j_\theta \cross \vec B_\phi &amp;#43; \vec j_\phi \cross \vec B_\theta = \grad p\] Eventually, the toroidal force balance will lead to the Grad-Shafranov Equation, which tells us how we can solve for a general equilibrium that solves \( \vec j \cross \vec B = \grad p \) .</description></item><item><title>Implicit Algorithms</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-4/</guid><description>Implicit Algorithms # Stability conditions are often related to the CFL number, and stability analysis of explicit algorithms usually require us to set a limit to small CFL
\[\left| \frac{a \Delta x}{\Delta t} \right| \leq 1\] For a given grid, this effectively sets a limit on the time step. The time step can be no larger than the grid spacing divided by the propagation constant \( \Delta t \leq \Delta x / |a| \).</description></item><item><title>Equilibrium of 3D Configurations</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/10-equilibrium-of-3d-configurations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/10-equilibrium-of-3d-configurations/</guid><description>Equilibrium of 3D Configurations # In 3 dimensions, we lose the axisymmetry that allowed us to reach the Grad-Shefranov equation and we need to solve the full momentum equation in three dimensions. This is not something that we can actually do in this class, and the existing codes that do this are quite sophisticated.
Some general features of 3D equilibria are:
No net toroidal current. This means that they tend to be steady-state configurations.</description></item><item><title>Numerical Boundary Conditions</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA543/ch21-5/</guid><description>Numerical Boundary Conditions # The linear advection equation is
\[\pdv{u}{t} &amp;#43; a \pdv{u}{x} = 0\] For it to be a well-posed mathematical problem, you also need the Cauchy data (boundary and initial conditions). From the order of the differential operators, we know that we need one boundary condition (constraint on \( u(x_b) \) for all \( t \) ) and one initial condition (constraint on \( u(x) \) at \( t = 0 \)).</description></item><item><title>MHD Stability</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/11-mhd-stability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/11-mhd-stability/</guid><description>MHD Stability # Equilibrium is simply a balance of forces that results in a steady state. Beyond equilibrium, stability is the tendency of a perturbation to return to equilibrium, rather than increasing. We are very interested in analyzing the stability of MHD equilibria, including the plasma dynamics, so we need to use the complete ideal MHD model. The MHD equations are non-linear, which means that any evolution/dynamics are also going to be non-linear.</description></item><item><title>The Electric Field</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-1/</guid><description>2.1: The Electric Field # 2.1.1: Introduction # The fundamental problem electrodynamics hopes to solve is this (Fig 2.1): We have some electric charges \( q_1, q_2, q_3, \ldots \) (call them source charges); what force do they exert on another charge, \( Q \) (call it the test charge)? The positions of the source charges are given (as functions of time); the trajectory of the test particle is to be calculated.</description></item><item><title>Divergence and Curl of Electrostatic Fields</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-2/</guid><description>2.2: Divergence and Curl of Electrostatic Fields # 2.2.1 Field Lines, Flux, and Gauss&amp;rsquo; Law # In principle, we are done with the subject of electrostatics. Eq. 2.8 tells us how to compute the field of a charge distribution, and Eq. 2.3 tells us what the force on a charge Q placed in this field will be. Unfortunately, as you may have discovered, the integrals involved in computing E can be formidable, even for reasonably simple charge distributions.</description></item><item><title>Electric Potential</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-3/</guid><description>2.3: Electric Potential # 2.3.1: Introduction to Potential # The electric field E is not just any old vector function. It is a very special kind of vector function: one whose curl id zero. \( \vec{E} = y \vu{x} \) , for example, could not possibly be an electrostatic field; no set of charges, regardless of their sizes and positions, could ever produce such a field. We&amp;rsquo;re going to exploit this special property of electric fields to reduce a vector problem (finding E) to a much simpler scalar problem.</description></item><item><title>Work and Energy in Electrostatics</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-4/</guid><description>2.4: Work and Energy in Electrostatics # 2.4.1: The Work it Takes to Move a Charge # Suppose you have a stationary configuration of source charges, and you want to move a test charge Q from point a to point b (Fig. 2.39). Question: how much work will you have to do? At any point along the path, the electric force on Q is \( \vec{F} = Q \vec{E} \); the force you must exert, in opposition to the electric force, is \( -Q\vec{E} \).</description></item><item><title>Conductors</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch2-5/</guid><description>2.5: Conductors # 2.5.1: Basic Properties # In an insulator, such as glass or rubber, each electron is on a short leash, attached to a particular atom. In a metallic conductor, by contrast, one or more electrons per atom are free to roam. (In liquid conductors such as salt water, it is ions that do the moving). A perfect conductor would contain an unlimited supply of free charges. In real life there are no perfect conductors, but metals come pretty close, for most purposes.</description></item><item><title>Laplace's Equation</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-1/</guid><description>3.1: Laplace&amp;rsquo;s Equation # 3.1.1: Introduction # The primary task of electrostatics is to find the electric field of a given stationary charge distribution. In principle, this purpose is accomplished by Coulomb&amp;rsquo;s law, in the form of
\[\vec{E}(\vec{r}) = \frac{1}{4 \pi \epsilon_0} \int \frac{\rho(\vec{r&amp;#39;})}{\gr ^2} \vu{\gr} \dd{\tau&amp;#39;} \label{3.1}\] Unfortunately, integrals of this type can be difficult to calculate for any but the simplest charge configurations. Occasionally we can get around this by exploiting symmetry and using Gauss&amp;rsquo;s law, but ordinarily the best strategy is first to calculate the potential, V, which is given by the somewhat more tractable</description></item><item><title>The Method of Images</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-2/</guid><description>3.2: The Method of Images # 3.1.1: The Classic Image Problem # Suppose a point charge q is held a distance d above an infinite grounded conducting plane (Fig. 3.10). Question: what is the potential in the region above the plane? It&amp;rsquo;s not just \( (1/4 \pi \epsilon_0) q / \gr \), for q will induce a certain amount of negative charge on the nearby surface of the conductor; the total potential is due in part to q directly, and in part to this induced charge.</description></item><item><title>Separation of Variables</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-3/</guid><description>3.3: Separation of Variables # In this section we shall attack Laplace&amp;rsquo;s equation directly, using the method of separation of variables, which is the physicist&amp;rsquo;s favorite tool for solving partial differential equations. The method is applicable in circumstances where the potential \( (V) \) or the charge density \( (\sigma) \) is specified on the boundaries of some region, and we are asked to find the potential in the interior.</description></item><item><title>Multipole Expansion</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch3-4/</guid><description>3.4: Multipole Expansion # 3.4.1: Approximate Potentials at Large Distances # If you are very far away from a localized charge distribution, it &amp;ldquo;looks&amp;rdquo; like a point charge, and the potential is - to good approximation - \( (1/4 \pi \epsilon_0) Q/r \), where \( Q \) is the total charge. We have often used this as a check on formulas for V. But what if \( Q \) is zero?</description></item><item><title>Polarization</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-1/</guid><description>4.1: Polarization # 4.1.1: Dielectrics # This chapter is all about what happens to an electric field when you take matter into account. Matter, of course, comes in many varieties - phase, composition, state, etc. - and depending upon which type of matter we&amp;rsquo;re dealing with, the electrostatic field response can be very different. Nevertheless, most everyday objects belong (at least, to good approximation) to one of two large classes: conductors and insulators (or dielectrics).</description></item><item><title>The Field of a Polarized Object</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-2/</guid><description>4.2: The Field of a Polarized Object # 4.2.1: Bound Charges # Suppose we have a piece of polarized material - that is, an object containing a lot of microscopic dipoles lined up. The dipole moment per unit volume P is given. Question: What is the field produced by this object (not the field that may have caused the polarization, but the field the polarization itself causes)? Well, we know what the field of an individual dipole looks like, so why not chop the material up into infinitesimal dipoles and integrate to get the total?</description></item><item><title>The Electric Displacement</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-3/</guid><description>4.3: The Electric Displacement # 4.3.1: Gauss&amp;rsquo;s Law in the Presence of Dielectrics # In Section 4.2 we found that the effect of polarization is to produce accumulations of (bound) charge, \( \rho_b = - \div \vec{P} \) within the dielectric and \( \sigma_b = \vec{P} \cdot \vu{n} \) on the surface. The field due to polarization of the medium is just the field of this bound charge. We are now ready to put it all together: the field attributable to bound charge plus the field due to everything else (which, for want of a better term, we call free charge, \( \rho_f \)).</description></item><item><title>The Linear Dielectrics</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch4-4/</guid><description>4.4: Linear Dielectrics # 4.4.1: Susceptibility, Permittivity, Dielectric Constant # In the first few sections of this chapter we did not commit ourselves as to the cause of P; we dealt only with the effects of polarization. From the qualitative essence of 4.1, though, we know that the polarization of a dielectric ordinarily results from an electric field, which lines up the atomic or molecular dipoles. For many substances, in fact, the polarization is proportional to the field, provided E is not too strong:</description></item><item><title>The Lorentz Force Law</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-1/</guid><description>5.1: The Lorentz Force Law # 5.1.1: Magnetic Fields # Remember the basic problem of classical electrodynamics: We have a collection of charges \( q_1, q_2, q_3, \ldots \) (the &amp;ldquo;source&amp;rdquo; charges), and we want to calculate the force they exert on some other charge Q (the &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; charge). According to the principle of superposition, it is sufficient to find the force of a single source charge - the total is then the vector sum of all the individual forces.</description></item><item><title>The Biot-Savart Law</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-2/</guid><description>5.2: The Biot-Savart Law # 5.2.1: Steady Currents # Stationary charges produce electric fields that are constant in time; hence the term electrostatics. Steady currents produce magnetic fields that are constant in time; the theory of steady currents is called magnetostatics.
By &amp;ldquo;steady current&amp;rdquo; I mean a continuous flow that has been going on forever, without change and without piling up anywhere (some people call them &amp;ldquo;stationary currents&amp;rdquo;; to my ear, that&amp;rsquo;s a contradiction in terms).</description></item><item><title>The Divergence and Curl of B</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-3/</guid><description>5.3: The Divergence and Curl of B # 5.3.1: Straight-Line Currents # The magnetic field of an infinite straight wire is shown in Fig 5.27 (the current is coming out of the page). At a glance, it is clear that this field has a nonzero curl (something you&amp;rsquo;ll never see in an electrostatic field); let&amp;rsquo;s calculate it.
According to Eq. 5.38, the integral of B around a circular path of radius s, centered at the wire, is</description></item><item><title>Magnetic Vector Potential</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch5-4/</guid><description>5.4: Magnetic Vector Potential # 5.4.1: The Vector Potential # Just as \( \curl \vec{E} = 0 \) permitted us to introduce a scalar potential (V) in electrostatics,
\[\vec{E} = - \grad \vec{V}\] so \( \div \vec{B} = 0 \) invites the introduction of a vector potential A in magnetostatics
\[\vec{B} = \curl \vec{A} \tagl{5.61}\] We were allowed to define these potentials based on our extended proof of the Helmholtz theorem (back in Section 1.</description></item><item><title>Magnetization</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-1/</guid><description>6.1: Magnetization # 6.1.1: Diamagnets, Paramagnets, Ferromagnets # If you ask the average person what &amp;ldquo;magnetism&amp;rdquo; is, you will probably be told about refrigerator decorations, compass needles, and the North Pole - none of which has any obvious connection with moving charges or current-carrying wires. Yet all magnetic phenomena are due to electric charges in motion, and in fact, if you could examine a piece of magnetic material on an atomic scale you would find tiny currents: electrons orbiting around nuclei and spinning about their axes.</description></item><item><title>The Field of a Magnetized Object</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-2/</guid><description>6.2: The Field of a Magnetized Object # 6.2.1: Bound Currents # Suppose we have a piece of magnetized material; the magnetic dipole moment per unit volume, M, is given. What field does this object produce? Well, the vector potential of a single dipole m is given by Eq. 5.85
\[\vec{A}_{dip} (r) = \frac{\mu_0}{4 \pi} \frac{\vec{m} \cross \vu{r}}{r^2}\] In the magnetized object, each volume element \( \dd \tau&amp;rsquo; \) carries a dipole moment \( M \dd \tau&amp;rsquo; \), so the total vector potential is (Fig 6.</description></item><item><title>The Auxiliary Field H</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-3/</guid><description>6.3: The Auxiliary Field H # 6.3.1: Ampere&amp;rsquo;s Law in Magnetized Materials # In Section 6.2, we found that the effect of magnetization is to establish bound currents \( \vec{J_b} = \curl \vec{M} \) within the material and \( \vec{K_b} = \vec{M} \cross \vu{n} \) on the surface. The field due to magnetization of the medium is just the field produced by these bound currents. We are now ready to put everything together: the field attributable to bound currents, plus the field due to everything else - which I will call the free current.</description></item><item><title>Linear and Nonlinear Media</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch6-4/</guid><description>6.4: Linear and Nonlinear Media # 6.4.1: Magnetic Susceptibility and Permeability # In paramagnetic and diamagnetic materials, the magnetization is sustained by the field; when B is removed, M disappears. In fact, for most substances the magnetization is proportional to the field, provided the field is not too strong. For notational consistency with the electrical case (Eq. 4.30), I should express the proportionality thus
\[\vec{M} = \frac{1}{\mu_0} \chi_m \vec{B} \tagl{6.</description></item><item><title>Electromotive Force</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-1/</guid><description>7.1 Electromotive Force # 7.1.1: Ohm&amp;rsquo;s Law # To make a current flow, you have to push on the charges. How fast they move, in response to a given push, depends on the nature of the material. For most sub- stances, the current density \( \vec{J} \) is proportional to the force per unit charge, \( \vec{f} \):
\[\vec{J} = \sigma \vec{f} \tagl{7.1}\] The proportionality factor \( \sigma \) (not to be confused with surface charge) is an empirical constant that varies from one material to another; it&amp;rsquo;s called the conductivity of the medium.</description></item><item><title>Electromagnetic Induction</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-2/</guid><description>7.2: Electromagnetic Induction # 7.2.1: Faraday&amp;rsquo;s Law # In 1831 Michael Faraday reported on a series of experiments, including three that (with some violence to history) can be characterized as follows:
Experiment 1:. He pulled a loop of wire to the right through a magnetic field (Fig 7.21a). A current flowed in the loop.
Experiment 2: He moved the magnet to the left, holding the loop still (Fig 7.21b). Again, a current flowed in the loop.</description></item><item><title>Maxwell's Equations</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch7-3/</guid><description>7.3: Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s Equations # 7.3.1: Electrodynamics Before Maxwell # So far, we have encountered the following laws, specifying the divergence and curl of electric and magnetic fields
\[\begin{aligned} (\text{i}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{E} = \frac{1}{\epsilon_0 } \rho \quad \text{(Gauss&amp;#39;s law)} \\ (\text{ii}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{B} = 0 \quad \text{(Ng&amp;#39;s Law)} \\ (\text{iii}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{E} = - \pdv{\vec{B}}{t} \quad \text{(Faraday&amp;#39;s Law}) \\ (\text{iv}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{B} = \mu_0 \vec{J} \quad \text{(Ampere&amp;#39;s Law)} \end{aligned}\] These equations represent the state of electromagnetic theory in the mid-nineteenth century, when Maxwell began his work.</description></item><item><title>Phys 544 Introduction</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-0/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-0/</guid><description>8.0: Phys 544 Introduction # Author Notes # From here on out, the text will be based on the lecture content, not on the Griffiths textbook. The class will follow the 4th edition pretty closely, but there will definitely be some differences. Hope I don&amp;rsquo;t get too much wrong!
Course Structure # We&amp;rsquo;ve got some real homework this time!
33% Homework, more or less weekly 33% Midterm. 1 hour, closed-book 33% Final + presentation.</description></item><item><title>Charge and Energy</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-1/</guid><description>8.1: Charge and Energy # As far as particles go, we&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the momentum and energy of charges. With fields, we have a similar situation. The fields determine what the particles do, and together with the energy/momentum of the particles themselves, the energy/momentum of the fields form a set of conservation laws
Conservation of Charge # We know that charge is conserved. You can&amp;rsquo;t create or destroy charge by itself - you must compensate by destroying or creating some other charge.</description></item><item><title>Momentum</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch8-2/</guid><description>8.2: Momentum # In this chapter we talk about:
Electromagnetic momentum Maxwell stress tensor Conservation of electromagnetic momentum Angular momentum in EM fields 8.2.1: Electromagnetic Momentum # As it turns out, if you disregard the momentum associated with electromagnetic fields, Newton&amp;rsquo;s laws appear not to work out! Consider a basic system in cartesian coordinates of two moving point charges:
What happens between the two charges? Well, the magnetic field of \( q_1 \) points into the page at \( q_2 \), so the magnetic force on \( q_2 \) is to the right, and the magnetic field of \( q_2 \) is out of the page at \( q_1 \) , so the magnetic force on \( q_1 \) is upward.</description></item><item><title>Student Lectures</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/90-student-lectures/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/90-student-lectures/</guid><description>\[\] Particle Diagnostics: Neutron diagnostics (Aria Johansen) # Start from the basics: what is a neutron? It&amp;rsquo;s a spin \( 1/2 \) baryon which interacts with all forces. Primarily decays into usually an electron and an antielectron neutron as well as a proton. Another decay process with 1/1000 of intensity decays to gamma. Mass is \( 939.6 MeV/c^2 \), very comparable to proton.
Where do neutrons come from? They decay quite rapidly - 15 minute lifetime.</description></item><item><title>Electromagnetic Waves in One Dimension</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-1/</guid><description>9.1: Electromagnetic Waves in One Dimension # 9.1.1 THE WAVE EQUATION # Before we start writing down how electromagnetic energy propagates in space as radiation, we&amp;rsquo;ll dust off our mathematical background on waves. Thanks to Fourier analysis, we know that sinusoidal waves form a complete basis for all periodic functions, so we restrict our investigation to sinusoidal variations.
Suppose some quantity &amp;ldquo;\( f \)&amp;rdquo; is propagating with speed \( v \) in the \( +z \) direction, and we focus on sinusoidal &amp;ldquo;disturbances.</description></item><item><title>My class lecture</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/91-zeeman-spectroscopy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/91-zeeman-spectroscopy/</guid><description>\[\] Zeeman Spectroscopy # Motivation # In high-energy-density plasmas, the current density distribution is strongly tied to the magnetic field distribution, and in some regions measurement of the B-field is the only way to obtain current density measurements. The magnetic field also determines resistivity, plasma dynamics, and energy balance.
The diagnostic methods to measure localized magnetic fields in plasma make use of the Zeeman effect, the Stark effect, Faraday rotation, or Faraday&amp;rsquo;s law.</description></item><item><title>Wave Equation for E and B</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-2/</guid><description>9.2.1 Wave Equation for E and B # Recall Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations
\[\begin{aligned} (\text{i}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{D} = \rho_f \quad \text{(Gauss&amp;#39;s law)} \\ (\text{ii}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{B} = 0 \quad \text{(Ng&amp;#39;s Law)} \\ (\text{iii}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{E} = - \pdv{\vec{B}}{t} \quad \text{(Faraday&amp;#39;s Law}) \\ (\text{iv}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{H} = \vec{J}_f &amp;#43; \pdv{\vec{D}}{t} \quad \text{(Ampere&amp;#39;s Law)} \end{aligned}\] To get to a wave equation from these, we start with a curl of curl and use a standard vector identity</description></item><item><title>Electromagnetic Waves in Matter</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-3/</guid><description>9.3: Electromagnetic Waves in Matter # 9.3.1: Propagation in Linear Media and Non-conductors # Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations in linear media are
\[\begin{aligned} (\text{i}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{D} = \rho_f \quad \text{(Gauss&amp;#39;s law)} \\ (\text{ii}) &amp;amp; \quad \div \vec{B} = 0 \quad \text{(Ng&amp;#39;s Law)} \\ (\text{iii}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{E} = - \pdv{\vec{B}}{t} \quad \text{(Faraday&amp;#39;s Law}) \\ (\text{iv}) &amp;amp; \quad \curl \vec{H} = \vec{J}_f &amp;#43; \pdv{\vec{D}}{t} \quad \text{(Ampere&amp;#39;s Law)} \end{aligned}\] In linear media, our constitutive relations are</description></item><item><title>Electromagnetic Waves in Conductors</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-4/</guid><description>9.4.1 Electromagnetic Waves in Conductors # When we formulated our description of how electromagnetic waves move through linear media, we relied on the stipulation that the free charge density \( \rho_f \) and free current density \( \vec J _f \) were zero. In the case of conductors, we&amp;rsquo;re going to need to re-visit that assumption.
As a refresher, when we last took a good look at conductors we had just moved beyond the electrostatic picture.</description></item><item><title>Guided Waves</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch9-5/</guid><description>9.5.1 Guided Waves # Moving beyond plane waves with infinite extent, now we consider waves confined to the interior to some sort of pipe, or wave guide. To make things simple, the overall geometry of the pipe should be large compared with the wavelength, and we&amp;rsquo;ll assume it&amp;rsquo;s made of a perfect conductor so there&amp;rsquo;s no loss (perfect reflection).
Monochromatic plane wave solutions will look like
\[\vec E(x, y, z, t) = \vec{E_0} (x, y) e^{i(kz - \omega t)}\] \[\vec B(x, y, z, t) = \vec{B_0} (x, y) e^{i(kz - \omega t)}\] The (source-free) boundary conditions within the waveguide are</description></item><item><title>Formulary</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/formulary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA545/formulary/</guid><description>\( \) Formulary # Kinetic Description
\[\dv{\vec v}{t} = \frac{q_i}{m_i} (\vec E &amp;#43; \vec v_i \cross \vec B) &amp;#43; \sum_{j \neq i} \left[ \left. \dv{\vec v_{ij}}{t} \right|_{coll} \delta(\vec r_i - \vec r_j) \right]\] \[\pdv{\vec B}{t} = - \curl \vec E\] \[\frac{1}{c^2} \pdv{\vec E}{t} = \curl \vec B - \mu_0 \sum_i q_i \vec v_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] \[\div \vec{B} = 0\] \[\div \vec E = \frac{1}{\epsilon_0} \sum_i q_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] Klimontovich equation:</description></item><item><title>Formulary</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/formulary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA558/formulary/</guid><description>\( \) Formulary # Kinetic Description
\[\dv{\vec v}{t} = \frac{q_i}{m_i} (\vec E &amp;#43; \vec v_i \cross \vec B) &amp;#43; \sum_{j \neq i} \left[ \left. \dv{\vec v_{ij}}{t} \right|_{coll} \delta(\vec r_i - \vec r_j) \right]\] \[\pdv{\vec B}{t} = - \curl \vec E\] \[\frac{1}{c^2} \pdv{\vec E}{t} = \curl \vec B - \mu_0 \sum_i q_i \vec v_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] \[\div \vec{B} = 0\] \[\div \vec E = \frac{1}{\epsilon_0} \sum_i q_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] Klimontovich equation:</description></item><item><title>Formulary</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/formulary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/UWAA560/formulary/</guid><description>\( \) Formulary # Kinetic Description
\[\dv{\vec v}{t} = \frac{q_i}{m_i} (\vec E &amp;#43; \vec v_i \cross \vec B) &amp;#43; \sum_{j \neq i} \left[ \left. \dv{\vec v_{ij}}{t} \right|_{coll} \delta(\vec r_i - \vec r_j) \right]\] \[\pdv{\vec B}{t} = - \curl \vec E\] \[\frac{1}{c^2} \pdv{\vec E}{t} = \curl \vec B - \mu_0 \sum_i q_i \vec v_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] \[\div \vec{B} = 0\] \[\div \vec E = \frac{1}{\epsilon_0} \sum_i q_i \delta (\vec r - \vec r_i)\] Klimontovich equation:</description></item><item><title>Scalar and Vector Potentials</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-1/</guid><description>10.0.1 Presentation/Paper notes # A few words about the paper/presentation
It&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be on a topic related to the class (classical electromagnetism) The topic can be wide-ranging. Some sample topics will be put it. It should be thematically related to what we&amp;rsquo;ve been talking about, and you should be making connections to things we&amp;rsquo;ve been talking about (waveguides, waves, generation of waves, etc.) There will be two class periods in the last week which are reserved for presentations of about 15 minutes each.</description></item><item><title>Retarded Potentials</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-2/</guid><description>10.2.1 Retarded Potentials # In the Lorenz gauge, we want to find the potentials by solving
\[\laplacian \vec A - \mu_0 \epsilon_0 \pdv{^2 \vec A}{t^2} = - \mu_0 \vec J\] Back in the static case, this reduces to Poisson&amp;rsquo;s equation
\[\laplacian V = - \frac{1}{\epsilon_0} \rho\] \[\laplacian \vec A = - \mu_0 \vec J\] and we know how to solve these
\[V(\vec r) = \frac{1}{4 \pi \epsilon_0} \int \frac{\rho(\vec r&amp;#39;)}{\gr} \dd \tau&amp;#39; \] \[\vec A(r) = \frac{\mu_0}{4 \pi} \int \frac{\vec J (\vec r&amp;#39;)}{\gr} \dd \tau&amp;#39; \] We know that electromagnetic disturbances travel at the speed of light (at least in vacuum).</description></item><item><title>Point Charges</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch10-3/</guid><description>10.3 Point Charges # 10.3.1 Moving Point Charges: Lienard-Wiechert Potentials # Suppose we have a point charge moving on some trajectory \( \vec w(t) \). If we naively read off the retarded potential
\[V(\vec r, t) = \frac{1}{4 \pi \epsilon_0} \int \frac{\rho(\vec r&amp;#39;, t_r)}{\gr} \dd \tau&amp;#39;\] might suggest that the potential is just
\[\frac{1}{4 \pi \epsilon_0} \frac{q}{\gr}\] But that&amp;rsquo;s wrong for a subtle reason: It is true that for a point source \( \gr \) comes outside the integral, but the remainder</description></item><item><title>Dipole Radiation</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch11-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/ch11-1/</guid><description>11.1 Dipole Radiation # 11.1.1 Electric Dipole Radiation # Consider a dipole which is &amp;ldquo;oscillating&amp;rdquo; at some particular frequency. This looks like two metal spheres separated by distance \( d \) and connected by a small wire; at time \( t \) the charge on the upper sphere is \( q(t) \) and the charge on the lower sphere is \( -q(t) \). We drive the charge back and forth through the wire from one sphere to the other at an angular frequency \( \omega \)</description></item><item><title>Solved Problems Ch3</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch3/</guid><description>Chapter 3 Solved Problems # \[\] Problem 3.24 # Q Solve Laplace&amp;rsquo;s equation by separation of variables in cylindrical coordinates, assuming there is no dependence on \( z \) (cylindrical symmetry). Make sure you find all solutions to the radial equation; in particular, your result must accomodate the case of an infinite line charge, for which we already know the answer. A Since we are in cylindrical coordinates, we will write Laplace&amp;rsquo;s equation in cylindrical coordinates \( (s, \phi, z) \):</description></item><item><title>Solved Problems Ch5</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch5/</guid><description>Chapter 5 Solved Problems # \[\] Problem 5.5 # Q A current I flows down a wire of radius a. (a) If it is uniformly distributed over the surface, what is the surface current density K? (b) If it is distributed in such a way that the volume current density is inversely proportional to the distance from the axis, what is J(s)? A K is the current per unit width \( \perp \) to the direction of the flow.</description></item><item><title>Solved Problems Ch7</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch7/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch7/</guid><description>Chapter 7 Solved Problems # \[\] Problem 7.7 # Q A metal bar of mass m slides frictionlessly on two parallel conducting rails a distance l apart. A resistor R is connected across the rails, and a uniform magnetic field B pointing into the page fills the region.
(a) If the bar moves to the right at speed v, what is the current in the resistor?
(b) What is the magnetic force on the bar?</description></item><item><title>Solved Problems Ch9</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch9/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/griffiths/problems-ch9/</guid><description>Chapter 9 Solved Problems # \[\] Review Problem 1 # Q Current-carrying wire with gap. A large diameter wire of cross-section area \( A \) carries current uniformly over its cross-section. There is a narrow gap of width \( d \), forming a parallel-plate capacitor. The current is zero for times \( t &amp;lt; 0 \) and the current is \( I \) at times \( t &amp;gt; 0 \).</description></item><item><title>Crews (2018)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/crews2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/crews2018/</guid><description>Development of a Collisionless Plasma Kinetic Solver and an Investigation of One-Dimensional Plasma Waves and Instabilities # Shielded potential of a test electron:
\[\phi(r) = \frac{-e}{4 \pi \epsilon_0 r} e ^{- r / \lambda_D}\] where the Debye length is \( \lambda_D = \sqrt{\frac{\epsilon_0 T_e}{ n_e e}} \) . The mean free path between large-angle collisions is estimated as
\[\lambda_{mfp} \sim \frac{\epsilon_0 T_e ^2}{\phi_e n_e \log ( \Lambda)}\] where \(\phi_e = e^2 / 4 \pi \epsilon_0\) are the constants from the Coulomb force law.</description></item><item><title>Datta (2021)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/datta2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/datta2021/</guid><description>\[\] A Domain-Hybridized Plasma Model Using Discontinuous Galerkin Finite Elements # Models # Keep in mind that the behavior of a plasma is primarily determined by the ratio between a spatial length of interest and the following reference lengths. The appropriate model for describing a plasma depends on the regime defined by these lengths.
Reference length Degree of magnetization Larmor radius \( r_L \) Charge separation Debye length \( \lambda_D \) Collisionality Mean free path \( \lambda_{mfp} \) Continuum Kinetic Model # The continuum kinetic model is the most complete description, taking into account the forces acting upon each particle:</description></item><item><title>Goedbloed (2019)</title><link>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/goedbloed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://peppyhare.github.io/r/notes/working/goedbloed/</guid><description>\[\] Thermonuclear fusion and plasma confinement # Nuclear reactions release net energy if there is a mass defect, i.e. if
\[(m_A) &amp;#43; m_B) c ^2 &amp;gt; (m_C &amp;#43; m_D) c^2\] In laboratory fusion, hydrogen isotopes are considered, where the deuterium-tritium reaction is the most promising one for future reactors:
\[D^2 &amp;#43; T^3 \rightarrow He ^4 (3.5 MeV) &amp;#43; n (14.1 MeV)\] This yields two kinds of products, viz. \( \alpha \) particles which are charged so that they can be captured by a confining magnetic field, and neutrons which are electrically neutral so that they can escape from the magnetic configuration.</description></item></channel></rss>